Finding Aid for the Qayani Collection of Arabic and Persian Manuscripts LSC.1053
UCLA Library Special Collections
Qayani Collection of Arabic and Persian Manuscripts
circa 1307-1883
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.1053
2.0 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942336293606533
Scope and Content
Collection consists of manuscripts in Arabic, Persian, and Turkish by or collected by the scholar, Sayyid Abu Talib bin Abi Turab al-Husayni al-Khurasani al-Qayeni (1818-1876).
Organization and Arrangement
Manuscripts 1-4, 6-8, 11-13, 15 (Box 1).
Manuscripts 16-23, 28 (Box 2).
Manuscripts 29-39 (Box 3).
Manuscripts 41-47, 50, 51 (Box 4).
Manuscripts 5, 9, 10, 14, 24-27, and 40 have been withdrawn.
Manuscript 48 moved to Collection 1117, Persian Medical Manuscript no.47.
Manuscript 49 moved to Collection 1117, Manuscript no.109.
manuscripts (documents) -- Arab countries.
- Durrah al-bahirah
  - "Kitab al-fawa'id al-gharawiyah" (fi 'ilm al-rijal: Biographics)., Dated: 1270 /1853.; 1; Arabic, Naskh, red titles, black leather binding; with autograph & signature (margin, p.234).; 235pp. of text; 17 lines per page; 215 × 130 (155 × 80) mm. (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Copy of the original prepared by 'Abd al-Razzaq b. Mahmud.
    Unedited.
  - "Kitab mira 'at al-wahda" (Mirror of [divine] unity)., Dated: 1293 / 1876.; 2; Persian, Naskh, red titles & red leather binding with ornamental borders, blue paper.; 397pp. of text; 11 lines per page; 170 × 110 (110 × 65) mm. (Box 1)
    Scribe: Asadullah b. 'Ali Akbar al-Birjandi.
  - "Kitab al-durrah al-bahirah" (Virginal pearl)., Dated: 1277 / 1860.; 3; Arabic with numerous Persian verses (pp.6, 59, 80,105 etc.); Black leather binding.; 111pp. of text; 11 lines per page; 175 × 110 (115 × 55) mm. (Box 1)
    Written down by the author himself and donated to his friend, 'Ali Riza al- Musawi, in 1278 / 1861 (s. notes and seal, pp.2, 111).
  - "Risalah fi ahkam al-salat wa al-siyam fi hal al-musafirat" (Prayer and fast on journeys)., Dated: 1279 / 1862.; 4; Arabic, Naskh, red tides, green leather binding. With autograph (p.1).; 145pp. of text; 11 lines per page; 155 × 110 (110 × 65) mm. (Box 1)
    Copy of the original prepared for the author by 'Abd al-Razzaq b. Mahmud.
  - Shaikh Baha'i., Dated: 1252 /1836.; 5; 216pp. of text & 7pp. of notes; 12 lines per page; Naskh, 205 × 105 (100 × 50) mm. Rarity.
    a) "Risalat khulasat al-hisab" (treatise on Mathematics), Arabic (89pp. of text)
    b) "Risalah-yi farsi-yi hay'at" (treatise on astronomy), Persian, preface, two maqalat, conclusion (127pp. of text with 10 tables and 27 drawings in two and three colors). Numerous comments by Qayeni in the margins. Black leather binding with ornamental border.
  - Risalah in reply to 'Abd al-Wahhab Qazwini, from the possessions of Qayeni and bearing his autograph (p.1). Approximately 1850 CE., 6; Arabic, Naskh, black leather binding with ornamental borders.; 59pp. of text; 16 lines per page; 155 × 100 (100 × 60) mm. (Box 1)
    Scribe: 'Abd al-Razzaq b. Mahmud.
  - Collection of 3 treatises on religious philosophy (Persian)., Dated: 1257 / 1841.; 7; 216pp. of text & 3pp. of notes; 16 lines per page; Naskh, red titles; brown leather binding; 150 × 100 (105 × 60) mm. (Box 1)
    a) "Nukhbah dar wajibat wa muhimmat-i diniyah" (on religious desiderata), pp.4-154.
    b) "Risalah dar sawm" (Tractate on fasting), pp.155-205.
    c) "Risalah dar khams wa haft" (Treatise on the meaning of the numbers 5 and 7), pp.205-216.
    Scribe (with seal): Muhammad 'Ali b. Mirza Mustafa.
  - "Kitab 'ibarat ra'iqah wa faqarat fayidah" (Arabic prose and [pp.99] ff). Dated (p.103):, 1264 / 1848.; 8; Persian quatrains, and the Qasida of Najib-Pasha Karbala'i; with autograph of the owner, Qayeni, (p.1); masterful Naskh calligraphy. Black leather binding with ornaments.; 103pp. of text; 12 lines per page; 170 × 110 (115 × 60) mm. (Box 1)
    Calligrapher: Shabhi Muhammad Salih b. Aqa Husayn Qoli (al-Shaqaqi).
  - Collection of poetry and science, with five titles, 9; 151pp. of text; 9-26 lines per page; 190 × 140 mm. Brown leather binding with ornaments.
    a) Notes, pp.1-3
    b) Abu Bakr al-Wali: "Akhbar al-Majnun wa ash'arihi (prose and poetry about Majnun and his love for Layla); dated (p.110): 1265 / 1849. Calligrapher (famous): Sharif Muhammad Sadiq, pp.4-115.
    c) Poetry (Fath Nasir-i Khaqani etc.), pp.116-135.
    d) 'Abd al-Qadir Ruyani: "Mukhtasari dar ma'rifat-i taqwinm" (treatise on astronomy and the science of calendars; preface, two abwab, khatimah), Persian, dated 1265 / 1849. Fine diagonal calligraphy by Mahmud b. Muhammad b. Isma'il, pp.136-142.
    e) Poetry (Rumi, Shams-i Tabrizi, etc.), pp.143-151.
  - Collection of six titles (Arabic, Persian), thereof two illuminated., Dated: 1301-08 H.; 10; 570pp. of text; 12-27 lines per page; Naskh and Nasta'liq; fine red leather binding with ornaments; 200 × 120 (135 × 70) mm.
    a) "Kitab-i durr-i lu'ali" (attributed to 'Ali b. Talib); calligrapher: Mirza Haydar 'Ali b. Karbala'i, pp.1-325.
    b) Notes (Imams, Abbasids, etc.), pp.326 ff.
    c) 'Aziz Safi: "Nuskhah-yi yadigari" (on medicinal drugs), pp.328 ff.
    d) "Min kalam amir al-mu 'minin" (quotes Muhyi al-Din al-'Arabi, Sadr al-Din, Hafiz 'Abd al-Qadir, etc.), pp.326 ff.
    e) "Kitab-i adwiyah-ye Mulla Sulayman" (pharmaceutics), pp.373-396.
    f) "Majmu'ah-yi 'irfan" (anthology of mysticism, prose & poetry); substantial; calligrapher as under(a), pp.397-570.
    Completely or largely unedited.
  - "Kitab kalamat zarifah wa maqalat sharifah". Dated by the author (pp.69/70): (i.e. 17 years prior to the author's death)., Sha'ban 1074 / 1663; 11; Arabic, in the fine, very clear script of the author (Naskh), with red titles and seals and notes by previous owners (pp.1-3, 70-72). Dark red leather binding with six ornamental medallions.; 72pp. of text; 15 lines per page; 190 × 105 (130 × 55) mm. Autograph. (Box 1)
  - "Ta'liqat 'ala hawashi sharh ai'Azadi bi-mukhtasir al-Hajibi" (three parts)., Dated (p.246) Rajab 1123 / 1711.; 12; Arabic, valuable in terms of calligraphy (exquisite Nasta'liq), lavish marginalia in finest miniscule script; notes and seal (p.1) by Muhammad b. Razi al-Din al-Harawi. Very fine brown leather binding with ornamental border and six decorative medallions.; 246pp. of text; 27 lines per page; 260 × 140 (205 × 80) mm. (Box 1)
    Calligrapher: Muhammad Rafi' b. Abu 'Ali al- Qazwini al-Taliqani.
  - "Kitab-i muhit-i bahr-i haqa'iq" (anthology, in 13 parts, of the Shaikhs Ahari, Abhari, Bakri, Baghdadi, Basri, 'Ajami, Dinwari, Ta'i, Ma'ruf al-Karkhi, Sjad, Saqti, Suhrawardi, et al.)., Dated (in accordance with lost original ?): Rabi' II, 853 / 1449.; 13; Persian, fine Nasta'liq with red titles. With 17 tables and drawings in two and three colors. Brown leather binding.; 370pp. of text; 19 lines per page; 230 × 155 (180 × 95) mm. Probably valuable rarity. (Box 1)
    Contents: 13 of the originally 14 parts are preserved: on prayer, sunna, the names of Allah, the nature of angels, talismans, numeric and and alphabetic mysticism, seclusion, resurrection, the 12th Imam, astrology, archery, wrestling, swordsmanship and horsemanship.
    Various parts are written in chiffre (abjad).
  - Collection: "Kitab-i usturlab" (Book of the astrolabe), three treatises on astronomy by famous authors; Persian, 14; 341pp. of text; 17 lines per page; 215 × 170 (160 × 90) mm; with 50 two-colored drawings and tables. Black leather binding.
    a) Baha' al-Din Muhammad al-Amili (Shaikh Baha'i): "Risalah-yi dar fann-i usturlab" (dedicated to the grand wazir, Mirza Hatim-Beg), 70 chapters (abwab), pp.1-47.
    b) Rukn b. Sharaf al-Din al-Amuli: "Kitab bab al-sultani" (based on Biruni and Farghani, composed by b. Harat in Rabi' II, 860 / 1456, dedicated to the wazir, Bahadur-Khan), pp.48-134.
    c) Husayn b. 'Ali al-Kashifi: "Kitab sab'i-yi kashifiyah" (on the planets, preface, two maqalat, conclusion), pp.137-341.
    Copy prepared by the calligrapher, Damghani in 1237-38 / 1822-23 (pp.47, 134, 341).
    General note
    Most probably unresearched.
  - "Kitab al-masadir" (Linguistics, Arabic and Persian), fine Naskh with ornamental titles and red sentence dividers., Dated: Jumadi I, 1104 / 1692.; 15; Burgundy leather binding.; 144pp. of text; 14 lines per page; 190 × 125 (140 × 80) mm. (Box 1)
    Title page bears 7 lines of notes signed by Husain b. 'Ali al-Hilli, dated 1111 / 1699, according to which the manuscript is declared a religious endowment (waqf) by Malik Husain al- Qayeni (signatures and seals of witnesses are also present).
    Calligrapher (a famous master): Dust Muhammad (p.144; cf. Bayani I, pp.187 ff., no.316: mentions merely one manuscript from the University Library in Istanbul).
  - "Kitab al-rawzah"., Dated: Ziy al-Qa'da 1060 / 1650.; 16; Arabic, fine & clear script with red titles and numerous marginalia. Dark brown leather binding.; 259 pages of text; 19 lines per page; 250 × 170 (175 × 100) mm. (Box 2)
    Calligrapher: 'Ali b. Husain Shirazi.
  - "Risalah-yi dar bayan-i adab-i hajj" (Treatise on pilgrimage practices)., Dated: Jumadi I, 1203 / 1788.; 17; Persian, Naskh. Brown leather binding with six ornamental medallions (narrow binding(?)).; 82pp. of text; 18 lines per page; 170 × 70 (135 × 50) mm. (Box 2)
    Calligrapher: Muhammad Taqiy b. Muhammad Sharif.
  - "Kitab rawzat al-safa" (First volume of the famous universal history: prophets and rulers of the pre-islamic world). (only eight or nine years after Mir-Khwand's death)., Dated (p.387): 912 / 1506; 18; Persian. Text boxes in gold, red, and blue; fine introductory ornaments (sar-luh) with floral designs in gold and colors. Heavy brown leather binding. (Spine and binding somewhat damaged).; 387pp. of text; 31 lines per page; 365 × 225 (285 × 170) mm. (Box 2)
    Exquisite Nasta'liq by an anonymous master Calligrapher.
    Rarity: one of the earliest Mir-Khwand manuscripts, at any rate
  - Collection of five titles, 19; (Persian, Arabic); 74pp. of text; 205 × 155 mm; brown leather binding. (Box 2)
    a) Abu Talib al-Qayeni autobiographical notes of the former owner (signed "Mirza Abu Talib"), pp.1-4.
    b) Poetry ("Mahmud Ayyaz"; lament of one of Mahmud's sons for the drowned beloved, quatrains by Sa'd b. Zangi, etc.), very fine Naskh with ornamental titles in red, pp.6-11.
    c) Comments and notes (prose and verse), pp.12 ff.
    d) Shaikh Baha'i: "Al-risalah ai-samadiyah"; Arabic, fine large Naskh with red titles and most lavish marginal comments in miniscule script; famous calligrapher: Muhammad Sharif (signed p.70), dated: Rabi' I, 1212 / 1797, pp.14-70.
    e) Shaikh Baha'i: "Az manzumat..." (poetry), pp.71 ff.
  - "Shark al-hidayah" (famous commentary on Athir al-Din al-Abhari, cf. Browne IV, p.57: "Maybodi's commentary... is still the favourite text-book for beginners in philosophy...")., Final dating (p.222): Shawwal 880 / 1475 (!!).; 20; Arabic, fine very even Naskh. Marginalia partially damaged (main text is immaculate). Brown leather binding (spine and binding somewhat damaged).; 222pp. of text; 15 lines per page; 190 × 105 (115 × 55) mm. (Box 2)
    "faraqtu min ta'lifihi..." without mention of a katib: copied directly from the original[?].
  - "Sharh suwar al-Qur'an" (Coranic commentaries)., Dated (pp.47, 318, 369): 1110 and 1117/1698 and 1705.; 21; Arabic; varying, always well legible script with red titles. Main body of text pp.29-318. Beginning, end, margins and pasted-in notes with a wide variety of marginalia. Semi-leather binding with painted ornaments in orange and blue.; 397pp. of text; 14 lines per page (main body of text); 190 × 125 mm. (Box 2)
    Scribe: Abu Turab Salim b. Rashid.
  - Collection of two treatises on linguistics (Arabic). approximately, 1750 C.E.; 22; 93pp. of text; 13 lines per page (main body of text); 150 × 100 mm; Two-colored leather binding (damaged). (Box 2)
    a) Ahmad b. 'Ali b. al-Mas'ud: "Kitab mirah al-arwah", pp.1-88.
    b) 'Abd al-Qahir al-Jurjani: "Risalah fi al-nahw...", pp.89-92.
  - "Risalah dar bari-yi sighah" (Treatise on Shi'ite temporary marriage)., Dated: Sha'ban 1301 / 1883.; 23; Persian, even, easily legible Naskh. Green leather binding; 106pp. of text; 11 lines per page; 165 × 105 (120 × 60) mm. Unedited autograph. (Box 2)
  - Collection of two treatises on astronomy, 24; (Persian); 244pp. of text, 220 × 160 (170 × 90) mm. 35 tables and drawings (red, black). Brown leather binding with ornamental border.
    a) Khajah Nasir al-Din Muhammad Tusi: "Risalah-yi si fasl" (Tractate on astronomy and science of calendars in 30 parts); beginning of first section missing; large Nasta'liq, 52pp. of text, 11 lines per page. Dated: Ramadan 1197 / 1783, p.52.
    b) Husain b. 'Ali Kaffashi: "Risalah-yi shams al-ma'arif" (Astronomical treatise based on Khwajah Tusi and the "Liwa'ah al-qamar fi al-ikhtiyarat" of Kamal al-Din Husain al-Wa'iz: s. pp.197 ff., 244); Nasta'liq, 21 lines per page; dated: Safar 1206 / 1791, pp.53-244.
  - "Risalah-yi farsi dar hay'at" (Persian treatise on astronomy), 25; pp.95-144 original (15th/16th century Nasta'liq), beginning (pp.1-94) replaced (18th century Naskh). Dark leather binding.; 144 pages of text; 12 lines per page; Nasta'liq and Naskh; 165 × 105 (110 × 55) mm. 20 astronomical drawings (red, black). 16th and 18th century (s.a.).
    One of the rare scientific works in Persian antedating 1500.
    Preface, two main sections (maqala), conclusion. Lavish comments in margins.
    Manuscript was owned by Mirza Dawud b. Mir Muhammad Ja'far al- Husaini al-Mashhadi in Rabi' II, 108 1793 (s. notes and seals pp.1, 144).
  - Collection of four treatises on medicine (Persian), 26; 477pp. of text; 23 lines per page; fine Nasta'liq with red titles; 250 × 155 (180 × 80) mm. Dark red leather binding with ornamental border.
    a) Mirza Muhammad Husain Afshar (student and translator of the court physician and professor at the "Dar al-funun," Dr J.B. Polak, 1818-91): "Kitab 'ilaj al-asqam" (surgery), Persian version of one of Dr. Polak's works: lithograph, Tehran 1273; Manuscript dated 1280 / 1863, 204pp. of text.
    b) "Lughat" (59 medical terms translated into Persian and commented), 2pp.
    c) "Risalah-yi kahhali" (on eye diseases; lithograph, Tehran 1273: s. Meshar II, p.701), preface and 12 chapters (abwab), scribe: 'Abd al-Husain, dated: Muharram 1280 / 1863 (original 1273), 64pp. of text.
    d) Afshar (based on Polak): "Makhzan al-fawa'id dar a'mal" (compiled by Riza-Quli), 101pp. of text.
  - Collection of 13 treatises and numerous drawings and tables., Dated: 1241 / 1825 and 1226-30 / 1714-18.; 27; 336pp. of text; 15-21 lines per page (main bodies of text); 210 × 150 mm; Leather binding covered with two-colored paper. As yet unedited.
    Scribe (pp.50-336): Muhammad b. 'Ali; pleasant Nasta'liq with red titles.
    Manuscript is divided into two parts: (A) no.1-4 (pp.1-49), (B) no.5-13 (pp.50-336).
    1) Tractate on religious ablutions, pp.1-8.
    2) "Siyagh al-'uqud wa al-iqat", pp.9-33; both by Shaikh 'Ali b. 'Abdullah.
    3) from: "Kitab ghayat al-maram...", pp.33-43.
    4) Treatise on marriage and divorce, pp.44-49.
    5) "Khulasah fi 'ilm al-hisab" (Summary of arithmetic); preface missing. Nine chapters (abwab) and khatimah. With 58 drawings and tables (red, black). Based on Shaikh Baha'i. Continuous comments in margins, signed: "Muradi," "Nizam al-Din," '"Abd al-Rahman," etc., pp.50-105.
    6) 'Umar b. Ahmad al-Ma'i: "Sharh al-risalah al-baha'iyah" (Discussion of Shaikh Baha'i's arithmetic); Arabic; with 25 drawings and tables, pp.107-212.
    7) "Risalah fi al-usturlab" (Science of the astrolabe); with one drawing (p.240). Preface, 15 chapters (fusul), conclusion, pp.214-241.
    8) "Risalah fi samt al-qiblah" (Treatise on the direction of prayer), p.242.
    9) Quotation from a risalah on the astrolabe, p.243.
    10) "Risalah fi al- 'amal bi al-rub' al-mudhayyib" (mathematics), preface and 20 abwab; marginalia signed "Abu Bakr al-Asiri," pp.245-260.
    11) Two tables (two-colored) with comments in fine minute script by Abu Bakr al-Asiri, p.261.
    12) Shihab al-Din Ahmad b. al-Majdi: "Risalah fi al-muqantarat" (mathematics); preface and 10 fusul. Appendix p.275. Marginalia signed "Ibn Hilli" etc. (pp.263-275). Appendix: seals and comments, pp.276 ff.
    13) "Risalah fi ma'rifat al-istikhraj" (Astronomy, calculations); Arabic; preface, 17 abwab, conclusion. Based on Shaikh Abu 'Abdullah Muhammad al-Maridini (s.p.280). Marginalia, pp.278-336.
    pp.50-336 of particular scientific interest.
  - "Hashiyah 'ala alfiyah al-shahid" (Commentary on the famous Shahid-Alfiyah). Written (cf. end note p.157)., before 1102 / 1690; 28; Arabic; large, easily legible Naskh with red titles on thick waxed paper. Completely preserved. Fine green leather binding with six ornamental medallions (blemished).; 157pp. of text; 16 lines per page; 190 × 125 (125 × 70) mm. (Box 2)
  - Collection (Title: "Kitab manhaj al-tullab"; 'The path of scholars') of three works (Arabic). Dated (pp.118, 149, 200, 274):, 1181 / 1767.; 29; Very even, easily legible, vocalized Naskh with red titles. Countless marginalia in the margins, between the lines, and pasted-in. Black leather binding with ornaments.; 274pp. of text; 17 lines per page (main bodies of text); 220 × 170 mm. Autograph. (Box 3)
    a) "Kitab al-taharat", pp.1-149.
    b) "Kitab al-nikahat", pp.151-200.
    c) "Kitab al-jinayat", pp.203-274.
    According to the preface (p.2), the author was influenced by Imam Shafi'i and Zakariya al-Nawawi.
  - "Asrar al-'arifin" (Secrets of the knowing; anthology of mystic Shi'ite prose and poetry)., Dated: 1256 / 1840.; 30; Persian and Arabic. Masterful calligraphic Naskh (black, red) with 13 two-colored title borders. Very nice brown leather binding with six ornamental medallions displaying flowers and birds.; 465pp. of text; 15 lines per page; 210 × 150 mm. (Box 3)
    Contents: Preface (beginning is missing), 19 main chapters (majalis), conclusion.
    Probably unedited.
  - Collection., Dated: Safar 1014 / 1605.; 31; 81pp. of text; 26 and 16 lines per page; 210 × 150 mm; four schematic drawings; scribe: Zayn al-Din Dizfuli, named '"Abbasi al-Muttali"(p.81). ( on (a), s. Enc.de l'Islam, I, II, pp.688 ff.) (Box 3)
    a) Abu al-Jaysh al-Andalusi (7th / 13th cent.) "Risalah fi 'ilm al-'aruz" (Treatise on the science of prosody); Arabic, fine, even Naskh with red titles
    b) Islamic legends of saints from the "Kitab-i jami'" (continuous in margins); Persian. Nasta'liq. Light leather binding with ornamental borders.
  - "Kitab fi ma'rifat al-rijal" (biographical material)., Original Dated: 707 / 1307 (Dated: 1186 / 1772).; 32; Arabic; even Naskh with red key words. Two initial sheets. Two-colored leather binding.; 104pp. of text; 15 lines per page; 180 × 110 (130 × 65) mm. (Box 3)
    Contains names and genealogies of 785 islamic celebrities.
    Two autographical notes and three seals of 'Abdullah b. 'Abd al- 'Azim al-Khwansari.
  - Collection of three titles., 33; 203pp. of text; 14-19 lines per page; 200 × 130 (130 × 60) mm. Two-colored leather binding with ornaments. (Box 3)
    a) Safi al-Din Muhammad b. Fazlullah b. 'Abdullah al-Razi: "Ikhtisar al-sharh al-musammah bi al-hanafiyah"; Arabic; with signature and seal of the author (p.1). Autograph (pp.1-6, 11-90, and numerous marginalia). (pp.1-90)
    b) Appendix (verses and notes); p.93; dated: 1209 / 1794. (pp.90-94)
    c) Anonymous: "Maqamat al-'arifin" (cf. H. Ritter, "The Sea of the Soul," p.656, according to whom this was composed in 771: Manuscript Koprulu 784) (pp.95-203).
  - "Sharh mukhtasar al-usul". Dated (p.681): 26. Sha'ban 7347 / 1334 (in words)., Signature and Seal Dated: 1200 / 1785.; 34; Arabic; Nasta'liq with red titles and copious marginalia. Manuscript was owned by the judge (qazi) of Maraghi (Ibn 'Abd al-Rahman; p.1).; 681pp. of text; 18 lines per page; 180 × 110 (120 × 65) mm. (Box 3)
  - "Mashariq al-anwar" (Places of lights, composed 774 / 1372)., Approximately 1700 CE.; 35; Arabic, fine clear Naskh with red titles. Two-colored leather binding with ornaments.; 407pp. of text; 18 lines per page; 210 × 120 (150 × 70) mm. (Box 3)
    Standard work, as yet little researched (cf. H. Corbin, "History of Islamic Philosophy," Paris 1964; p.56: "an essential work for Shi'ite gnosis ...").
  - Collection of two works., Dated: 1014 / 1605.; 36; 538pp. of text; 7-17 lines per page; 190 × 125 (120 × 50) mm. (Box 3)
    a) 'Aziz b. Muhammad al-Razawi (scribe / author (?)): "Mabadi al-lughat" (Philology); Arabic; even Naskh with numerous marginalia, pp.1-262.
    b) Qazi Baizawi (died 685 / 1186): "Minhaj al-wusul"; Arabic; large Naskh with red titles; preface and seven books, pp.263-538. Fine brown leather binding with clasp.
    Scribe (b): Muhammad Hadi. (p.262; (a)), 1039 / 1629 (p.538 (b)).
  - "Sharh bab al-hadi 'asharah"., Approximately 1750 C.E.; 37; Arabic; large, clear Naskh with red titles; numerous marginalia, frequently signed ("Sayyid Sadr al-Din"). Two-colored leather binding.; 222pp. of text, 12 lines per page; 150 × 100 (115 × 50) mm. (Box 3)
  - "Nijat al-'ibad fi yawm at-mi'ad" (parts I-IV)., 38; Beautiful, large Naskh with red titles. Brown leather binding.; 259pp. of text; 19 lines per page; 220 × 155 (150 × 85) mm. (Box 3)
    Persian translation by Isfahani's student, Sayyid Abu Talib Hamadani.
    A 1293 / 1876 lithograph from Tehran is itself considered to be a rarity.
    Manuscript possibly translator's autograph.
  - Collection of three titles. Dated (p.356):, Shawal 1074 / 1663.; 39; Large, even, partially vocalized Naskh with red titles, numerous marginalia, Arabic. Fine, heavy leather binding (two-colored) with ornamental border and medallions; ornamental clasp. Heavy waxed paper.; 519pp. of text; 25 lines per page; 210 × 150 mm. Rarity. (Box 3)
    a) "Kitab al-sawa'iq", pp.1-356.
    b) "Tatimmat" (Appendix to (a)), pp.357-393.
    c) "Kitab al-i'lam bi qawati'al-islam", pp.397-514.
    Scribe: Mahfuz al-Ghamri.
  - Collection of seven treatises. Dated (pp.23, 56, 62, 111):, 1085-87 / 1674-76.; 40; Varying script with red titles and many geometrical and schematic drawings. Semi-leather binding. Arabic and Persian.; 168 pages of text, 15-23 lines per page; 190 × 140 mm.
    Mostly compilations, on:
    1) Mysticism of love ("al-'ashiqin"), pp.1-23.
    2) Scholastic theology ("mukhtasari az risalah-yi 'ilm-i kalam"), pp.24-56.
    3) Avicenna, pp.57-62.
    4) Poetry, prosody, pp.64-82.
    5) Geometry (by Qazizadah Rumi), pp.83-111.
    6) Astronomy and astrology (by Muhammad b. 'All al-Tumani), pp.112 ff.
    7) Metaphysics, pp.156 ff.
    Scribe, compiler, and (partially) author: Mustafa b. 'Ali Sadiq al- Sirini (Kurdistan, cf.p.56).
  - "Kitab a'mal-i sal wa faza'il-i ayyam" (Book of meditation and contemplation, divided in accordance with the months of the Islamic calendar; dedicated to Shah Sultan Husain). Copy Dated Rajab:, 1225 / 1810.; 41; Persian; with numerous quotations in Arabic; fine script (Nasta'liq & Naskh) in golden, red and black frames with red titles. Fine brown leather binding.; 385pp. of text; 18 lines per page; 150 × 100 (115 × 65) mm. (Box 4)
  - "Diwan." Dated:, approximately 1750 C.E.; 42; Persian; large, easily legible Nasta'liq with frames in gold, red, and black.; Black leather binding with ornamental medallions and cloth spine with floral patterns in gold and colors.; 400pp. of text; 15 lines per page; 200 × 135 mm. (Box 4)
    Accurate copy of the edition prepared by Muhammad Gulandam after the poet's death.
    Contains:
    (a) Introduction, in prose, to the poet and his oeuvre, pp.1-10.
    (b) Qasidahs, pp.11-30.
    (c) Ghazals, pp.31-400.